questions = [ {"April":[
    {
        "question": "1. Recently, which country of East Africa was hit by the tropical cyclone named \u2018Gamane\u2019?",
        "options": [
            "Madagascar",
            "Tanzania",
            "Kenya",
            "Mauritius"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Madagascar]"
    },
    {
        "question": "2. Maravakandy Dam, recently seen in news, is located in which state?",
        "options": [
            "Tamil Nadu",
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Maharashtra",
            "Telangana"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Tamil Nadu]"
    },
    {
        "question": "3. Recently, which two countries have partially joined the Schengen area, the ID-check-free travel zone in Europe?",
        "options": [
            "Poland and Spain",
            "Romania and Bulgaria",
            "Sweden and Portugal",
            "Denmark and Ireland"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [Romania and Bulgaria ]"
    },
    {
        "question": "4. Recently, where was the Nepal-India International Sanskrit Conclave held?",
        "options": [
            "Pokhara, Nepal",
            "New Delhi, India",
            "Kathmandu, Nepal",
            "Varanasi, India"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: C [Kathmandu, Nepal]"
    },
    {
        "question": "5. Clean Energy Transitions Programme annual report 2023, recently released by which government agency?",
        "options": [
            "International Energy Agency (IEA)",
            "Bureau of Energy Efficiency (BEE)",
            "Ministry of Power",
            "Ministry of Petroleum and Natural Gas"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [International Energy Agency (IEA) ]"
    },
    {
        "question": "6. Chamayavilakku festival, recently seen in news, is associated with which state?",
        "options": [
            "Kerala",
            "Tamil Nadu",
            "Maharashtra",
            "Telangana"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Kerala]"
    },
    {
        "question": "7. What is the rank of India\u2019s \u2018GeM portal\u2019 as an e-commerce platform in the world?",
        "options": [
            "First",
            "Second",
            "Third",
            "Fifth"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: C [Third]"
    },
    {
        "question": "8. What is the theme of World Autism Awareness Day 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Empowering Autistic Voices",
            "The Transition to Adulthood",
            "Inclusive Quality Education for All",
            "Assistive Technologies, Active Participation"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Empowering Autistic Voices]"
    },
    {
        "question": "9. Deanna Syme Tewari, who recently passed away, was associated with which sports?",
        "options": [
            "Long Jump",
            "Boxing",
            "Wrestling",
            "Hockey"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Long Jump]"
    },
    {
        "question": "10. Where was the 19th annual meeting of the secretaries of the security councils of the SCO held?",
        "options": [
            "Dushanbe, Tajikistan",
            "Astana, Kazakhstan",
            "Tashkent, Uzbekistan",
            "Bishkek, Kyrgyzstan"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [Astana, Kazakhstan]"
    },
    {
        "question": "11. Recently, which airport became the 14th airport in India to launch the Digi Yatra system?",
        "options": [
            "Jay Prakash Narayan Airport, Bihar",
            "Shaheed Bhagat Singh International Airport, Chandigarh",
            "Manohar International Airport, Goa",
            "Devi Ahilyabai Holkar Airport, Madhya Pradesh"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: C [Manohar International Airport, Goa]"
    },
    {
        "question": "12. Sannati Bhddhist site, recently seen in news, is located in which state?",
        "options": [
            "Karnataka",
            "Odisha",
            "Bihar",
            "Kerala"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Karnataka]"
    },
    {
        "question": "13. Which country recently declared the EL-Nino induced drought a national disaster?",
        "options": [
            "Botswana",
            "Namibia",
            "Mozambique",
            "Zimbabwe"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: D [Zimbabwe]"
    },
    {
        "question": "14. What type of comet is the \u201cMother of Dragons\u201d comet, recently seen in news?",
        "options": [
            "Halley Comet",
            "Tempel Comet",
            "Encke Comet",
            "Kuiper Belt Comet"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Halley Comet]"
    },
    {
        "question": "15. Recently, a special website named \u2018Booth Raabta\u2019 has been launched in which state to provide election-related information to the people?",
        "options": [
            "Madhya Pradesh",
            "Haryana",
            "Punjab",
            "Uttar Pradesh"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: C [Punjab]"
    },
    {
        "question": "16. According to RBI, what is the projected Consumer Price Index (CPI) inflation for the fiscal year 2024-25 (FY25)?",
        "options": [
            "3.2%",
            "4.5%",
            "5.1%",
            "5.5%"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [4.5%]"
    },
    {
        "question": "17. Arrokoth, a double-lobed object in space, is located in which region of solar system?",
        "options": [
            "Kuiper Belt",
            "Oort Cloud",
            "The outer solar system",
            "The inner solar system"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Kuiper Belt]"
    },
    {
        "question": "18. Peter Pellegrini recently became the new president of which country?",
        "options": [
            "Norway",
            "Slovakia",
            "Denmark",
            "Romania"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [Slovakia]"
    },
    {
        "question": "19. Sukhna Wildlife Sanctuary, recently seen in news, is located in which state/UT?",
        "options": [
            "Chandigarh",
            "Ladakh",
            "Odisha",
            "Uttarakhand"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Chandigarh]"
    },
    {
        "question": "20. Ujung Kulon National Park, which was seen in the news, is located in which country?",
        "options": [
            "Indonesia",
            "Malaysia",
            "Romania",
            "China"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Indonesia]"
    },
    {
        "question": "21. What is the primary objective of Science Based Targets initiative (SBTi), recently seen in news?",
        "options": [
            "Limiting global warming to well below 2\u00b0C above pre-industrial levels",
            "Promoting organic farming in North India",
            "Promoting sustainable exploration of marine resources",
            "To promote corporate social responsibility"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Limiting global warming to well below 2\u00b0C above pre-industrial levels]"
    },
    {
        "question": "22. How much tree cover has India lost since 2000, according to the latest data from the Global Forest Watch monitoring project?",
        "options": [
            "3.13 million hectares",
            "1.23 million hectares",
            "3.25 million hectares",
            "2.33 million hectares"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: D [2.33 million hectares ]"
    },
    {
        "question": "23. Recently, which country launched first Angara-A5 space rocket?",
        "options": [
            "Russia",
            "China",
            "Japan",
            "India"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Russia]"
    },
    {
        "question": "24. Jonatan Christie, who recently won his first Asian Badminton Championship, belongs to which country?",
        "options": [
            "Vietnam",
            "Thailand",
            "Singapore",
            "Indonesia"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: D [Indonesia]"
    },
    {
        "question": "25. Kuchipudi dance, recently seen in the news, is a classical dance form of which state?",
        "options": [
            "Tamil Nadu",
            "Andhra Pradesh",
            "Maharashtra",
            "Uttar Pradesh"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [Andhra Pradesh]"
    },
    {
        "question": "26. What was the primary objective of \u2018Operation Meghdoot\u2019, recently mentioned in news?",
        "options": [
            "To establish a military base in Ladakh",
            "To capture strategic heights in the Himalayas",
            "To engage in a peacekeeping mission",
            "To secure the Siachen Glacier"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: D [To secure the Siachen Glacier]"
    },
    {
        "question": "27. Recently, which Indian stadium becomes the first BCCI-accredited venue with a new \u2018hybrid pitch\u2019?",
        "options": [
            "Wankhede stadium, Maharashtra",
            "Himachal Pradesh Cricket Association (HPCA) stadium",
            "Ekana Cricket Stadium, Lucknow",
            "Barabati Stadium, Cuttack"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [Himachal Pradesh Cricket Association (HPCA) stadium]"
    },
    {
        "question": "28. Lake Kariba, recently seen in news, is located between which two countries?",
        "options": [
            "Zambia and Zimbabwe",
            "Tanzania and Congo",
            "Djibouti and Ethiopia",
            "Burundi and Zambia"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Zambia and Zimbabwe]"
    },
    {
        "question": "29. Which day is celebrated as \u2018World Hemophilia Day\u2019 every year?",
        "options": [
            "16 April",
            "17 April",
            "18 April",
            "19 April"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [17 April]"
    },
    {
        "question": "30. Who becomes the first Indian to venture into space as a tourist on the NS-25 mission of Blue Origin?",
        "options": [
            "Gopi Thotakura",
            "Santosh Kulangara",
            "Rajeev Aggarwal",
            "Sanjay Sinha"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Gopi Thotakura ]"
    },
    {
        "question": "31. Which institution recently green lighted investments in the country\u2019s Sovereign Green Bonds (SGrBs) by Foreign Institutional Investors (FIIS)?",
        "options": [
            "RBI",
            "SIDBI",
            "NABARD",
            "HDFC"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [RBI]"
    },
    {
        "question": "32. What is the theme of \u2018World Liver Day 2024\u2019?",
        "options": [
            "Keep your liver healthy and disease-free",
            "Be Vigilant, Get Regular Liver Check-Ups",
            "keep your liver healthy and disease-free",
            "Spreading awareness about liver-related issues"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Keep your liver healthy and disease-free]"
    },
    {
        "question": "33. Recently, who has been selected for the Malcolm Adiseshia Award 2023?",
        "options": [
            "Vikas Kumar",
            "Utsa Patnaik",
            "Sushma Sinha",
            "Prabhat Patnaik"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [Utsa Patnaik]"
    },
    {
        "question": "34. Mount Ruang, recently seen in the news, is located in which country?",
        "options": [
            "Malaysia",
            "India",
            "Indonesia",
            "Russia"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: C [Indonesia]"
    },
    {
        "question": "35. Capri city, recently seen in news, is located in which country?",
        "options": [
            "Iraq",
            "France",
            "Italy",
            "Russia"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: C [Italy]"
    },
    {
        "question": "36. Recently, who became the youngest male chess player to win the FIDE Candidate Tournament?",
        "options": [
            "Ding Liren",
            "D Gukesh",
            "Arjun Erigassi",
            "Nihal Sarin"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [D Gukesh]"
    },
    {
        "question": "37. Recently, which ministry has issued the directive to eliminate commercial dealing in organs, especially those involving foreign citizens?",
        "options": [
            "Ministry of Agriculture",
            "Ministry of Health and Family Welfare",
            "Ministry of Housing and Urban Affairs",
            "Ministry of Power"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [Ministry of Health and Family Welfare]"
    },
    {
        "question": "38. Recently, which international university is assessing efficacy of a Geoengineering method under Marine Cloud Brightening (MCB) Programme?",
        "options": [
            "University of Cambridge",
            "Stanford University",
            "University of Pennsylvania",
            "University of Washington"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: D [University of Washington]"
    },
    {
        "question": "39. Recently, where was the 4th meeting of Intergovernmental Negotiating Committee (INC-4) on UN Plastics Treaty held?",
        "options": [
            "Sydney, Australia",
            "Ottawa, Canada",
            "Paris, France",
            "Hyderabad, India"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [Ottawa, Canada]"
    },
    {
        "question": "40. Eravikulam National Park, recently seen in news due to project Nilgiri Tahr, is located in which state?",
        "options": [
            "Kerala",
            "Odisha",
            "Karnataka",
            "Maharashtra"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Kerala]"
    },
    {
        "question": "41. Recently, which country passed the Safety of Rwanda (Asylum and Immigration) Bill?",
        "options": [
            "United Kingdom",
            "Canada",
            "France",
            "Russia"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [United Kingdom ]"
    },
    {
        "question": "42. Recently, which bank has signed an agreement with Tata Power Solar Systems to provide loans under the PM Surya Ghar Muft Bijli Yojana?",
        "options": [
            "Indian Bank",
            "UCO Bank",
            "State Bank of India",
            "Bank of Baroda"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: A [Indian Bank]"
    },
    {
        "question": "43. Mount Elgon National Park, recently seen in news due to Marburg virus, is located in which country?",
        "options": [
            "Uganda",
            "Tanzania",
            "Rwanda",
            "Kenya"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: D [Kenya]"
    },
    {
        "question": "44. Recently, which country has appointed Col.Edison Napyo as the first Defence Adviser of India?",
        "options": [
            "New Zealand",
            "Tonga",
            "Fiji",
            "Papua New Guinea"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: D [Papua New Guinea]"
    },
    {
        "question": "45. Subrahmanya Dhareshwar, who recently passed away, was a famous singer of which folk dance?",
        "options": [
            "Bharatanatyam",
            "Yakshagana",
            "Kuchipudi",
            "Kathakali"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [Yakshagana]"
    },
    {
        "question": "46. Recently, which space organization successfully launched its Advanced Composite Solar Sail System spacecraft from New Zealand?",
        "options": [
            "JAXA",
            "NASA",
            "ISRO",
            "CNSA"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [NASA]"
    },
    {
        "question": "47. Harshit Kumar, who recently won a gold medal in the 21st U-20 Asian Athletics Championship 2024, belongs to which sports?",
        "options": [
            "Javelin throw",
            "Hammer throw",
            "Tennis",
            "Chess"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [Hammer throw]"
    },
    {
        "question": "48. What is nephrotic syndrome, recently mentioned in the news?",
        "options": [
            "A skin disorder",
            "A kidney disorder causing excessive protein in urine",
            "A respiratory condition",
            "A neurological disorder"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [A kidney disorder causing excessive protein in urine]"
    },
    {
        "question": "49. Chakisaurus nekul, recently seen in news, belongs to which species?",
        "options": [
            "Spider",
            "Herbivorous dinosaur",
            "Lizard",
            "Frog"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: B [Herbivorous dinosaur]"
    },
    {
        "question": "50. Recently, which Indian has been selected for the \u2018Goldman Environmental Prize 2024\u2019?",
        "options": [
            "Rajendra Singh",
            "Tulsi Gowda",
            "Alok Shukla",
            "Ramesh Agrawal"
        ],
        "answer": "Correct Answer: C [Alok Shukla]"
    }
]
}
]
